<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<protocol name="xr_shell_unstable_v1">
  <copyright>
    Copyright © 2019 Status Research &amp; Development GmbH.

    Permission is hereby granted, free of charge, to any person obtaining a
    copy of this software and associated documentation files (the "Software"),
    to deal in the Software without restriction, including without limitation
    the rights to use, copy, modify, merge, publish, distribute, sublicense,
    and/or sell copies of the Software, and to permit persons to whom the
    Software is furnished to do so, subject to the following conditions:

    The above copyright notice and this permission notice (including the next
    paragraph) shall be included in all copies or substantial portions of the
    Software.

    THE SOFTWARE IS PROVIDED "AS IS", WITHOUT WARRANTY OF ANY KIND, EXPRESS OR
    IMPLIED, INCLUDING BUT NOT LIMITED TO THE WARRANTIES OF MERCHANTABILITY,
    FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE AND NONINFRINGEMENT.  IN NO EVENT SHALL
    THE AUTHORS OR COPYRIGHT HOLDERS BE LIABLE FOR ANY CLAIM, DAMAGES OR OTHER
    LIABILITY, WHETHER IN AN ACTION OF CONTRACT, TORT OR OTHERWISE, ARISING
    FROM, OUT OF OR IN CONNECTION WITH THE SOFTWARE OR THE USE OR OTHER
    DEALINGS IN THE SOFTWARE.
  </copyright>

  <description summary="an extended reality (XR) shell">
    TODO: Describe overall protocol here

    Warning! The protocol described in this file is experimental and
    backward incompatible changes may be made. Backward compatible changes
    may be added together with the corresponding interface version bump.
    Backward incompatible changes are done by bumping the version number in
    the protocol and interface names and resetting the interface version.
    Once the protocol is to be declared stable, the 'z' prefix and the
    version number in the protocol and interface names are removed and the
    interface version number is reset.
  </description>

  <interface name="zxr_view_v1" version="1">
    <description summary="a perspective from which the scene is viewed">
      zxr_view_v1 represents a perspective from which the scene is shown, for
      example from each eye of a head-mounted device (HMD).

      For wl_buffer types which submit multiple buffers, the client must prepare
      a buffer for every view global. If they fail to do so, the compositor may
      skip rendering the affected surface. If a view global is removed and the
      client
    </description>

    <!-- TODO: Resolution event (and subpixel?) -->

    <request name="destroy" type="destructor">
      <description summary="destroy zxr_view_v1">
        Sent when the client will no longer use this XR view.
      </description>
    </request>
  </interface>

  <interface name="zxr_shell_v1" version="1">
    <request name="create_composite_buffer">
      <description summary="create a composite buffer">
        Creates a new zxr_composite_buffer_v1. See the documentation for its
        interface for details.
      </description>
      <arg name="id" type="new_id" interface="zxr_composite_buffer_v1" />
    </request>

    <request name="get_xr_surface">
      <description summary="create xr surface from a surface">
        This request creates a zxr_surface_v1 for the given surface. This
        assigns the xr_surface role to the surface.

        See the documentation for zxr_surface_v1 for more details on how the
        interface is used.
      </description>
      <arg name="id" type="new_id" interface="zxr_surface_v1"/>
      <arg name="surface" type="object" interface="wl_surface"/>
    </request>
  </interface>

  <interface name="zxr_surface_v1" version="1">
    <description summary="a surface which is shown in a 3D scene">
      An XR surface represents a surface which is shown in a 3D scene. In order
      for the surface to be presented, the client must obtain an
      zxr_surface_view_v1 for each zxr_view_v1 global currently in use by the
      compositor, and submit a buffer which contains enough information to
      present the surface on each view. The actual usage requirements for these
      surface-views varies between different kinds of 3D buffers, but the client
      is required to create a surface-view for all active XR views regardless.

      If a client fails to provide surface-views for all XR views currently in
      use, the compositor may present a placeholder object, skip rendering the
      surface, or another behavior of their choosing, for one or more of the
      affected views. It is recommended that the compositor does not draw a
      surface for which left and right eye buffers are not available for the
      same HMD. A client which submits frames too slowly may be subject to
      similar treatment. In an XR environment, latency can result in physical
      sickness to the user, therefore it's very important to prepare new frames
      quickly.

      The surface-local coordinate space of an XR surface is defined by the
      attached buffer interface.

      It is a protocol error to attach a 2D buffer to an XR surface.
    </description>

    <enum name="error">
      <entry name="invalid_buffer" value="0"
        summary="client attempted to attach a 2D buffer to this surface" />
    </enum>

    <request name="get_surface_view">
      <description summary="get a surface-view for the given xr view">
        Creates a zxr_surface_view for this surface. Clients must create a
        surface-view for every zxr_view_v1 advertised by the compositor.
      </description>
      <arg name="surface_view" type="new_id" interface="zxr_surface_view_v1" />
      <arg name="view" type="object" interface="zxr_view_v1" />
    </request>
  </interface>

  <interface name="zxr_surface_view_v1" version="1">
    <event name="mvp_matrix">
      <description summary="update the model-view-projection matrix">
        The server sends this event to update the model-view-projection matrix
        for this surface-view's perspective. The client should prepare its next
        frame using this matrix.
        <!-- TODO: Explain what a model view projection matrix is? -->
      </description>
      <arg name="mvp_matrix" type="array"
        summary="4x4 matrix of 32-bit IEEE floating point numbers in row-major order" />
    </event>
  </interface>

  <interface name="zxr_composite_buffer_v1" version="1">
    <description summary="a buffer containing one 2D buffer for each XR view">
      An XR composite buffer consists of several 2D buffers, one for each XR
      view, which is composited directly onto the XR scene. There may be several
      kinds of buffers for a single view; for example a pixel buffer and a depth
      buffer.

      The surface-local coordinates for surfaces with a composite buffer
      attached are defined from (-1, -1) to (1, 1), and correspond to X and Y
      positions across the VR scene when projected into two dimensions.
      <!-- TODO: From which view's perspective? -->

      If a client attaches a composite buffer to a zxr_surface_v1 without
      attaching a 2D buffer for each XR view, they are subject to the
      contingency behaviors explained in the zxr_surface_v1 interface.
    </description>

    <enum name="error">
      <entry name="invalid_buffer" value="0"
        summary="client attempted to attach an invalid buffer or buffer type" />
    </enum>

    <enum name="buffer_type">
      <entry name="pixel_buffer" value="0" summary="A buffer of pixels" />
      <entry name="depth_buffer" value="1"
        summary="A buffer where each 'pixel' represents a depth value" />
    </enum>

    <request name="attach_buffer">
      <description summary="attaches or updates a buffer for a view">
        Attaches or updates a 2D buffer which has been prepared for a specific
        XR view. The buffer may be set to null to clear the buffer for this
        view, which is used mainly when the compositor has sent the
        zxr_view_v1.finished event for that view. If you set the buffer twice
        for the same view and buffer type, the buffer for that view/type will be
        updated.
      </description>
      <arg name="view" type="object" interface="zxr_view_v1"
        summary="view this buffer is prepared for" />
      <arg name="buffer" type="object" interface="wl_buffer" allow-null="true"
        summary="2D buffer to attach for this view" />
      <arg name="buffer_type" type="uint" enum="buffer_type"
        summary="buffer_type for this buffer" />
    </request>

    <request name="get_wl_buffer">
      <description summary="create a wl_buffer for this composite buffer">
        Gets a wl_buffer for this composite buffer, which may then be attached
        to a zxr_surface_v1.
      </description>
      <arg name="buffer" type="new_id" interface="wl_buffer"
        summary="the newly created wl_buffer"/>
    </request>
  </interface>

  <!--
    TODO:
    - Add better timing information? Prepare frames in advance? Map OpenXR more
      closely onto this protocol.
    - 3D geometry buffers, e.g. glTF
    - 2D buffers with left/right views, for e.g. 3D movies
  -->
</protocol>
